[SPEAKER_00]: I wanted to speak about this sutta in the Samyutta Nikaya 39.16.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it's with Venerable Sariputta.
[SPEAKER_00]: He's been asked a question.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's a short sutta.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'll read it out quickly.
[SPEAKER_00]: Venerable Sariputta, in this teaching and training, in this dhamma and discipline,
[SPEAKER_00]: What is hard to do?
[SPEAKER_00]: And he answers, the going forth is difficult to do in this dhamma and discipline.
But what's hard to do for someone who has gone forth?
When you've gone forth, it's difficult to be satisfied.
Contented.
Oh, yeah, it's difficult to be contented.
But what's hard, what's difficult to do for someone who's contented?
When you're content, it's hard to practice in line with the teaching.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then you ask, but if a renunciant practices in line with the teaching, will it take them long to become a perfected one?
[SPEAKER_00]: And he replies, it won't take them long.
[SPEAKER_00]: I thought that was very nice, you know, it's quite simple.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's kind of, well, just... just go forth.
[SPEAKER_00]: You know, learn to be content.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: And practice.
[SPEAKER_00]: And in no long time, you will have the result.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So the... yeah, exactly, the contentment needs to be learned.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, you have to learn how to be contented because, you know, you won't be able to sustain
[SPEAKER_01]: Practicing in line with the dhamma on the same level all the time.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you're gonna have ups and downs.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the contentment is important, for when you have your downs, you don't go lower than being contented within the homeless life.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, then you can easily and quickly carry on practicing when it picks up.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you are not contented,
[SPEAKER_01]: With the life of someone who has gone forth, then, when you experience the downs, the mind will want to go back to, like, you know, household life, basically.
[SPEAKER_01]: So that's why it's important to be contented.
[SPEAKER_01]: Whether your practice is going good or not, whether you're inspired or not, contentment is a kind of a basis that will sort of sustain that state of having gone forth.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which, of course, that means at any given time, the possibility of picking up the practice along the right lines remains there for you.
[SPEAKER_01]: You haven't excluded yourself from it, to say it like that.
[SPEAKER_00]: What comes to mind is a person who goes forth and starts the training of virtue and sensuous strength.
[SPEAKER_00]: It is difficult, but then
Yeah, so he... it's difficult to sustain.
But then, having sustained it, you know, you can become accomplished in virtue, accomplished in sentient state, and feel the joy on account of that accomplishment, you know.
Yeah.
So... and now you always have that joy to... to sustain you, to fall back on.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can't fall... you don't fall below that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, and that's...
[SPEAKER_01]: I think that's exactly... yeah, that's... those are the suttas where the Buddha said,
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, you should replace the joys of a household life with the joys of a renunciate life.
[SPEAKER_01]: You should replace the grief and sadness of a household life with the grief and sadness of a renunciate life.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you're still gonna have ups and downs, but if you're contented with that life, means you have upgraded, at least in that sense.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, because joys and griefs of a household life are much worse, much more pressuring, entangling, proliferated, and so on, than those of a renunciate life.
[SPEAKER_01]: There are still joys ups and downs, but they're purer, to say that way, because you are withdrawn from that, you know, household life is crowded and dusty, as they say, so...
[SPEAKER_00]: And the life gone forth is open air.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Open.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's fresh.
[SPEAKER_01]: Freer.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's clean.
[SPEAKER_00]: But... and I like what is, you know, what is... it's difficult to go forth.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's difficult to give up that which is familiar to you, that which which you know, that which you're comfortable in.
[SPEAKER_01]: Let's say it like that.
[SPEAKER_01]: So...
[SPEAKER_01]: Change is unpleasant, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's difficult to undergo such a change of giving up a household life for something that you are uncertain about and something that will require you to learn how to be contented with.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's why it's difficult to give it up, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: And anybody who is trying to give it up realizes that it's difficult to give it up.
[SPEAKER_00]: But giving up, giving it up and going forward,
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm keeping the precepts, virtue, you know, for taking refuge in the Buddha for the rest of your life, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_00]: You know, I will maintain this virtue.
[SPEAKER_00]: I will maintain the central strength.
[SPEAKER_00]: It says, you know, the Buddha says, you know, if you do that, you will experience a joy.
[SPEAKER_00]: A joy of being blameless.
A joy of being unpolluted.
Yeah, eventually.
Joy of... eventually.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which, you know,
[SPEAKER_00]: Once you, once you have that, it's, eh... then it's easier.
[SPEAKER_01]: What is?
For the practice.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, yeah, yeah, of course.
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, in Manisutta, it's said that, you know, joy arises on account of unbroken virtue, contentment, contented and joyous mind gets composed.
[SPEAKER_01]: So samādhi is born out of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, yeah, it's like a necessary basis.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's part of the practice, really.
[SPEAKER_01]: Learning how to be content with a homeless life, it's already, in a way, practicing along the lines of the dhamma.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: In terms of, you know, you read that you will become happy and feel a blameless joy if you
Maintain your virtue.
And which is, you know, you'll feel a blameless joy.
So, and you're not really doing anything.
You're just not doing wrong things.
And that joy is accessible to you.
Just reflecting on your sīla, sīla nusati, that joy is, you know, experienced.
Yeah.
You know, you know, there's
I was once dirty, now I'm quite clean.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it's funny how just that first step, you know, the Buddha says, keep this and you'll be happy.
[SPEAKER_00]: You know, you'll feel this blameless joy.
That first step is kind of... not many people have faith in just that first step, which is... it's so accessible, actually.
It's so close.
That very lofty pleasure is so close, you know, it's accessible.
Yet, it's like, I don't have faith in that.
I'd rather, I'd rather do something else.
I'd rather do meditation.
The satipaṭṭhāna instead.
But that's not the first step.
So, do you have faith in the Buddha?
Do you have faith in
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, that's that kind of lack of clarity that sort of exists in many people.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even if they have genuine intention to practice, they don't realize that, you know, your views of what the practice is, what's important for the practice, are views affected with ignorance.
[SPEAKER_01]: So,
[SPEAKER_01]: Your practice, actually, should start by questioning those views, questioning your motivation, uncovering and revealing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Your practice shouldn't start with just taking for granted the views that you have about a practice and practicing on account of them.
[SPEAKER_01]: And many people fall into that trap in a sense of they get the idea of what the practice is,
[SPEAKER_01]: They, eh... obviously, you know, you develop standpoints of what's important, what's not, and then you just... they just take it for granted that that's what the practice is, that's what the Buddha was teaching.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, they can profess, you know, that they're follower of the of the Buddha's teaching and the dhamma and so on, yet, as you say, exactly, the very first thing that the Buddha says you should do, they kind of overlooked.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's quite easily done, when your standpoints are already far away from what's really important.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's why, like the Buddha said, the most blameworthy thing is the wrong view.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the reason for everything unwholesome, in a way.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because if a person were to learn, or just start actually questioning themselves rightly, in a sense of, hold on, yes, I have faith that the Buddha was enlightened,
[SPEAKER_01]: I have faith that the dhamma is well expounded.
[SPEAKER_01]: I have faith that if I follow that dhamma, I can also, you know, reach some stage of enlightenment, free myself from suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, am I actually following clearly and understanding what the Buddha said and practicing on account of it?
[SPEAKER_01]: Or is my idea of, you know, I'm a Buddha follower, kind of, and I have faith in dhamma abstractly, but practically I'm doing something else.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, what do I put first?
[SPEAKER_01]: Am I doing my meditation for the sake of enlightenment?
[SPEAKER_01]: Or have I really developed the unbroken, unblemished aggregate of virtue, whereby I just recollect it and I experience pleasure on account of it?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because that's what the Buddha said you should do.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you shouldn't be doing that meditation before you've done that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, if you start questioning as to see if you're actually doing what the Buddha said you should do,
[SPEAKER_01]: Not doing what you think the Buddha said you should do.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, make the effort.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or, if you are absolutely convinced, then, again, it will do you no harm to re-evaluate it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And, if you arrive at the same answers, great.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, you have to be honest with yourself.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if you are, you would see that, well, there are certain things that the Buddha said you should do.
[SPEAKER_01]: And, have I done those things?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because, yes, something as simple as developing virtue, well, the Buddha said, if you actually develop it rightly, yes,
[SPEAKER_01]: Simply recollecting that, recollecting the Buddha and the Saṅgha, it will it will fill me with joy and samādhi.
[SPEAKER_01]: Is that the case?
[SPEAKER_01]: When I recollect my virtue, am I joyous?
[SPEAKER_01]: Am I contented?
[SPEAKER_01]: Am I sort of withdrawn from unwholesome states simply on account of that recollection?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, if the answer is no, then your idea of virtue and your practice of virtue is obviously not fulfilled.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not fulfilled from the Buddhist standpoint of view, from the point of view of practicing the dhamma.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you could ignore it and carry on thinking it's fine, or you could just say to yourself, hold on, why don't I fulfill this?
[SPEAKER_01]: It is something very straightforward, hard to misunderstand, easy to overlook, but hard to misunderstand if you look at it.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not complex.
[SPEAKER_01]: The reason people don't do it is not because it's just, oh, I don't understand what I'm supposed to do.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, it's because they overlook it.
[SPEAKER_01]: They just drift and do something else, or do something on top of it, instead of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Already at the expense of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So that's kind of the point.
[SPEAKER_01]: That honesty and self-reflection.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then you would re-evaluate things you think you know.
[SPEAKER_01]: And again, by reading the suttas, you would see quite clearly what the first thing to do is.
[SPEAKER_01]: And as we said in the opening, that you realize what that is already.
[SPEAKER_01]: By developing your virtue,
[SPEAKER_01]: Contentment, on account of the unblemished aggregate of virtue, you are practicing in line with the dhamma.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's not like, oh, I'll do that and then I'll do the dhamma.
[SPEAKER_01]: That is already doing the dhamma rightly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because, as the Buddha said, even within the five precepts, somebody keeping the five precepts, if they do it in that responsible sense, purified until it's... until the aggregate of that virtue is developed, until it's like, oh, I have been keeping the five precepts, have not intentionally went against them for a long time, the recognition of that will arise.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the Buddha said, so even within those five precepts, if a person then recollects that unblemished five precepts and virtue, recollects the Buddha, the dhamma and the saṅgha, that is their unification of mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: That is their samādhi.
[SPEAKER_01]: A factual samādhi arises as a result of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: The aggregate of samādhi comes from that aggregate of sīla.
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly, exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's why it's samādhi, because you're not doing it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're not creating it through your own sort of, you know, contrived techniques and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's the result of the aggregate of virtue.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's the result of your practice, which revolved around self-control and abstaining from unwholesome things, things rooted in unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you sustain that long enough, that samādhi will follow.
[SPEAKER_01]: Samādhi will be result of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now, when you are composed on account of contentment,
[SPEAKER_01]: That arose because of your unbroken virtue.
[SPEAKER_01]: Your unbroken virtue will be purified even further.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because, you know, being composed means not being as pressured or not being pressured as much.
[SPEAKER_01]: As if... as when you are pressured when you're not composed and then the mind gets pulled and pressured by various things that sort of you have to resist.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, composure that arises on account of the virtue will then feed and help the virtue and sustain the virtue further.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't have to lean the situation further, you know, abandoning the hindrances, you know, just...
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, you can then start refining it and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: In order to refine something, first you need to get rid of the crude impurities.
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, there are many similes like purifying the gold.
[SPEAKER_01]: You know, you don't just ignore all the junk around the gold dust and then start purifying the specific... No.
[SPEAKER_01]: First, you have to get rid of all of that.
[SPEAKER_01]: There is just simply no other way to get to the refined points.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that will become apparent to a person if they do actually, as we say, often start questioning their own motivation.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, okay, I want to meditate.
[SPEAKER_01]: Meditation helps me.
[SPEAKER_01]: I keep the precepts.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, okay, so why?
[SPEAKER_01]: What do I expect from meditation?
[SPEAKER_01]: What do I want to gain from it?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because
[SPEAKER_01]: If I'm keeping the precepts rightly, if I have developed the aggregate of virtue rightly, that should already be my meditation.
[SPEAKER_01]: That should already be the joy and gladness, a form of composure, should already arise in my mind, simply on account of that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yet, here I am, stressed about the environment changing that will prevent me from meditating and doing a technique or whatever I'm into.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's like...
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that doesn't sound right.
[SPEAKER_01]: It certainly doesn't sound like something the Buddha was describing.
[SPEAKER_01]: And, as I said many times before, it is, you know, it obviously it all stems from that view that people kind of just naturally pick up when they start learning about Buddhism, which is kind of, okay, so all the problems, all the stress, all the pressure that I'm experiencing,
[SPEAKER_01]: It comes because I miss the moment of my thought, or I haven't been focused hard enough.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if I never miss, never skip a beat, if my mindfulness is every second to a second, if I'm observing my thoughts clearly, constantly, evenly, all the time, suffering will diminish and I will not suffer.
[SPEAKER_01]: And Yuri the Suttas and the Buddha said quite clearly that
[SPEAKER_01]: That's not the reason for suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: The reason for one being affected by pressure, stress, and everything else, is your choices are still bound, are still rooted in greed, aversion, delusion.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, your choices still actively maintain greed, aversion, delusion, i.e.
[SPEAKER_01]: taṇha, the craving.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, presence of craving means presence of suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: And if you start realizing that, then you see that the whole practice of, you know, watching moment to moment, moment to moment, was basically nothing other than simply like a coping mechanism.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if you realize that the gateway of all of your problems, it's not like because your mindfulness skipped a beat.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's because your body, your speech, and your mind, still,
[SPEAKER_01]: have actions that are rooted in greed, aversion, delusion on some level.
[SPEAKER_01]: And those actions of greed, aversion, delusion are not subconscious.
[SPEAKER_01]: They're not kind of extra millisecond quick, where you must have developed this focus to spot them.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: They're always on the level of your conscious choice, which means they're always known and consequently, they're always covered up.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you need to
[SPEAKER_01]: That self-honesty, you need to uncover them and admit to yourself what you already know.
[SPEAKER_01]: And, as I said before, if anybody, like, you know, starts this this self-questioning, they will arrive at that point where they're clearly gonna see a compromise that they are aware of, that they are making, on account of which they try to compensate.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_01]: If, on the other hand, I give up the compromise, I don't have to do any of this.
[SPEAKER_01]: That was the missing part for my aggregator virtue.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if I would have a day where there is nothing pressuring me, no major event that would be sort of pulling me for distraction, entertainment and so on, great!
[SPEAKER_01]: So, I could spend the whole day then in a mindful state.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't need to do anything else.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just keep an eye on that gateway.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, content.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's exactly the form of contentment.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, if you ignore the fact that you're still making compromises on account of greed, aversion, distraction, then, everything else will become a compensation for it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, actually, it's like... it's... it seems harder initially.
[SPEAKER_01]: Seems, like, more unpleasant initially.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, eh... it's not.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you... if you take that as a standard, you realize all these other things, all these other burdens of virtue and duty, that you have taken upon yourself as practice, will stop burdening you, because they will not be your duty anymore.
[SPEAKER_01]: Your duty is to not act out of greed, aversion, delusion.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, your duty is to not give in to a conscious choice,
[SPEAKER_01]: I'll do this because I'm pressured by the desire.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'll do this because I'm pressured by ill-will.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'll do this because I'm indolent and I want to distract myself.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's all you need to do from the moment you wake up to the moment you go to sleep.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you do that, you will be unable to break the precepts.
[SPEAKER_01]: You will be unable to be discontented and you will be unable to not be composed.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not being unable to not be practicing in line with
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, even if you don't think, oh, now I should practice in line with the dhamma, you will be practicing in line with the dhamma.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's why I said, oh, how do we know, Master Gautama, what is in line with the dhamma, what it isn't?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, whatever brings dispassion, not passion.
[SPEAKER_01]: Whatever is inclined towards solitude, not company.
[SPEAKER_01]: Towards disentanglement, not entanglement.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, even if you don't necessarily want to give up the household life just yet, the principle remains the same.
[SPEAKER_01]: You want to keep your mind free from disturbances and calm?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, keep an eye on the doorway of choice of acting out of greed, aversion, delusion.
[SPEAKER_01]: And don't cover that up.
[SPEAKER_01]: Everything else put aside.
[SPEAKER_01]: Any sense of, oh, but I must do this, and I must do that, and I must practice ānāpānasati, and I must... No.
[SPEAKER_01]: You must develop the virtue that's unblemished, unbroken, until it becomes an aggregate on its own.
[SPEAKER_01]: Something you're not doing.
[SPEAKER_01]: anymore.
[SPEAKER_01]: Something that's kind of there, because you've been abstaining from certain things long enough.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, all you need to do is protect that virtue.
[SPEAKER_01]: It will give you the context.
[SPEAKER_01]: It will give you the samādhi on account of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because, again, the doorway of where all the problems come in, is greed, aversion, delusion.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not lapse of mindfulness or not enough focusing.
[SPEAKER_00]: You are training yourself to see that doorway clearer and clearer and clearer.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: And training to see where that doorway is, it's not on the level of training your focusing practice.
[SPEAKER_01]: They will then reveal the glimpse of the doorway.
[SPEAKER_01]: The doorway is not a glimpse.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not a split second.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's the entire context that basically directs your entire day.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, your entire day, actions throughout that day, choices you're making, are very conscious things.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's where the doorway is.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you don't need the focusing to see the doorway.
[SPEAKER_01]: You need honesty to see it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, initially, like, oh, okay, I will not engage with unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, the stress and the pain of pressure will be there, will increase.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, you realize, okay, what do I do now?
[SPEAKER_01]: I do the same thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now, on account of this pain and pressure, I will still not engage with anything unwholesome, including trying to get rid of this pain and pressure, because I'm so averse to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the principle remains unchanged, the practice remains the same.
[SPEAKER_01]: What increases is the pressure on account of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you realize, oh, so it means I'm doing it right.
[SPEAKER_01]: What happens is people take on the virtue of self-control, pressure increases, and then quickly give me a meditation technique to relieve me of this pressure.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it's like, well, no, actually, you're not supposed to relieve yourself from it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're supposed to not break the precepts on account of it, and that's how you will calm down.
[SPEAKER_00]: I was thinking, you know, you can... so you can...
You do all this renunciation and this pressure is building up.
It's unpleasant.
And then you can realize that it's unpleasant because I'm doing it correctly.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm cleaning it out.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, oh yeah, I'm doing it correctly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Isn't that great?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, that's that other other other talks we mentioned.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, the pressure that's building up on account of your renunciation is not because of the renunciation.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's because of that which you are renouncing.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, your renunciation reveals, basically, what you were under, what was controlling you, reveals your addiction.
[SPEAKER_01]: And abstaining from the addictive substance,
[SPEAKER_01]: So it feels like there is no problem up until I started saying no to myself.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like saying no to yourself only has revealed what you were already victim of, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, in order to develop that aggregate of virtue, correctly, eh... whether you are a layperson or a summoner,
[SPEAKER_01]: You will also then see, like, the role of patience.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why that patience is important.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not, you know, not like, not in that sense, oh, be patient.
[SPEAKER_01]: Patience is important and it's a virtue.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, it's like a, it's, it's, it's a, it's a thing you can do and develop and, you know, it's useful to remind yourself of it, because withdrawing from things that pressure you will, will, will reveal that, as I said, the, the pain of that pressure, it will increase it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, unless you have patience to bear it, you will then give in to that, eh... motivation and need and craving to get rid of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you might not break the precepts, but you still want to get rid of the discomfort that they revealed.
[SPEAKER_01]: And how'd you do that?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, you do that by following, eh...
[SPEAKER_01]: Tradition, technique, practices in that impersonal manner.
[SPEAKER_01]: And by that, I mean in that, like, oh, I just do that because that's what we are supposed to do.
[SPEAKER_01]: I do that because that's what technique tells me to do.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you will find ways of doing things in that... in a way that would basically mask your responsibility for it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because that's how you will alleviate the discomfort that a virtue placed upon you.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you must actually not do that.
[SPEAKER_01]: You mustn't give in to those ways of management, even if they seemingly are aligning themselves with the dhamma practice.
[SPEAKER_01]: The point is, you are doing them because you want to manage the discomfort.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't want to endure it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, in other words, you are acting out of craving against the unpleasant feeling.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's why you cannot be free from craving just yet, because you keep maintaining it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's why virtue in itself
[SPEAKER_01]: Without a right view, without right instruction, will just be virtue, you know.
[SPEAKER_01]: It will not necessarily give rise to understanding of the Four Noble Truths and the way out of suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the discomfort that comes on account of virtue, sense restraint, self-control, is... that's... that discomfort mustn't be, eh... covered up, eh... dismissed, ignored,
[SPEAKER_01]: Or, or, or, you know, got rid of.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that discomfort must be accepted.
[SPEAKER_01]: You must be patient in regard to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You must actually look more at your attitude of gratuitously trying to get rid of the discomfort, then you should be looking at the discomfort.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, if you want to practice samādhi within that, well, you will realize, okay, samādhi within the discomfort.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not at the expense of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not instead of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, samādhi doesn't mean disappearance of discomfort.
[SPEAKER_01]: Samādhi means I am now unmoved by any discomfort.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's a very different thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not necessarily externally looking by what you're doing, but internally it's rooted in a completely different intention.
[SPEAKER_01]: One is wholesome, another one is unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's why that patience
[SPEAKER_01]: It's necessary for you to endure the discomfort without habitually trying to get rid of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because then, again, you're still acting on the level of that sense response.
[SPEAKER_01]: Pleasing, give it to me.
[SPEAKER_01]: Displeasing, get rid of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's exactly what it means by, you know, even meditation is rooted in sensuality.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's still the same principle.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if you're patient with it, able to endure it sufficiently enough, you will learn how to calm yourself within it, not the expense of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And, of course, you will see what the true problem is, which wasn't the discomfort.
[SPEAKER_01]: That was not the root of suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: Your craving against it was the root of suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, then, all you need to do is recollect the virtue.
[SPEAKER_01]: On account of which, you're already patient and contented, and you will already be calm, regardless of whether it's comfort or discomfort around you, because you know exactly what not to do.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you don't need to worry about, then, what should I do, because you're not trying to get rid of the pain gratuitously anymore.
Just refining, refining, refining your breath.
Hm.
Are the same principles from the start?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Engaging with anything unwholesome and craving is unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if the pain feels like, oh, the pain is too much, I don't know what to do, well, fine, but you know exactly what not to do.
[SPEAKER_01]: Don't break the precepts, don't compromise the virtue, do everything else within that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Don't neglect sense restraint and so on, which means, okay, so, I don't need to do anything, as long as I don't do things I know I shouldn't be doing.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's how you actually calm yourself within that which is pressuring you and which you're enduring.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because people are always pressured internally by that.
[SPEAKER_01]: What do I do?
[SPEAKER_01]: How do I react?
[SPEAKER_01]: What, you know, what is my next move in order to deal with this?
[SPEAKER_01]: Which all carries that view, that kind of, this must be dealt with.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you're burdened by that.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the pain of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you realize, actually, I don't need to do anything.
[SPEAKER_01]: I know what I'm not going to do.
[SPEAKER_01]: I know what I'm... what I shouldn't be doing, but that requires no effort now, because I've been following that lifestyle for a while.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, you're not burdened by any response or any... any sort of figuring it out.
[SPEAKER_01]: It doesn't really matter.
[SPEAKER_01]: All that matters is to not do what you know you're not supposed to do.
[SPEAKER_01]: Act out of great aversion and delusion.
It's a hard thing to do.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Initially.
[SPEAKER_01]: But then, the more you do it, the easier it becomes.